International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, Aeronautical Industrial District Lodge 91 Records 1984.0017
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers Aeronautical Industrial District Lodge 91 Records
undated, 1937-1983
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1984.0017
95 Linear Feet
District Lodge 91 received its charter in May 1953. At that time the representative locals consisted of Hartford Aircraft Lodge 743, chartered in 1941, representing workers at Hamilton Standard (located in East Hartford until 1952 when it moved to Windsor Locks); Industrial aircraft Lodge 1746, chartered in February, 1945, representing workers at Pratt and Whitney, East Hartford; and Industrial Aircraft Lodge 1746A, chartered in October, 1951, representing Pratt and Whitney workers in Southington. In March 1959 Canal Lodge 700, in Middletown, was chartered and added to District 91 representation. Prior to 1953, Pratt and Whitney workers' lodges were part of IAM District 26. As of 1984, District 91 included Lodge 700, Lodge 707 (from North Haven), Lodge 743, Lodge 1746, and Lodge 1746A.
Access
The collection is open and available for research with the exception of to arbitration, grievance and legal case materials. Contact the curator for access to these materials.
Acquisition Information
The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, Aeronautical Industrial District Lodge 91 records were deposited in the Connecticut Labor Archives in February 1984 by Mel Tripp, Jr., President of District 91, and Charles A. Tracey, District Representative. Materials in the various legal series were given to the district by their legal counsel, Zeman and Daly, after the cases were complete.
Arrangement
Series I: Administrative records (1947-1982) is further divided into eight subseries: Correspondence and Subject Files (1947-1966) and Correspondence and Subject Files (1967-1982) are comprised of working papers generated and received by the President and the administrative officers of District 91. These files are useful in getting a broad overview of the range of activities in which the District was active. Materials of interest include correspondence form Grand Lodge, bylaws of District 91, minutes of district executive board meetings, correspondence with local lodges, National Labor Relations Board material, correspondence with the union's legal counsels and 1960 strike and settlement material. Materials in both subseries are arranged alphabetically by name, title or subject. Strike Material (circa 1960-1963) contains arbitration hearing transcripts, correspondence, and votes about the 1960 strike settlement. When used in conjunction with the strike-related material in the two Correspondence and Subject Files subseries and the legal series, these materials will provide comprehensive coverage of the 1960 strike and subsequent settlements. Material in this subseries is arranged alphabetically by type. Legal Case Files (circa 1966-1972) contains materials collected by the District 91 administrative office relating to the various cases that the District was involved in. Most of the material was sent to the District from the legal counsels and duplicated in several legal subseries. Individual cases are in separate section; the court hearing the case arranges other cases. Boron Cases (1969-1976) contains materials dealing with Lodge 743 activities at the Boron Filament Plant, Hamilton Standard Division of United Aircraft Corporation. Material includes contract negotiations and agreements, administrative and correspondence files, and legal case files. The 1970 contract negotiation material is of particular interest. Materials are arranged alphabetically by type. Preference for Bargaining Survey (1974) contains detail summary analysis of the responses to the 1974 survey of union members on preferred bargaining unit. The material is arranged by lodge. Lou Kiefer Files (circa 1960-1982) contains incoming and outgoing correspondence, reports and papers collected by G. Lou Kiefer in his role as Public Relations Officer and Editor of the New Union News for District 91. Materials are divided into two sections, correspondence and administrative files; folders are arranged alphabetically within each section. Dave Cooper Files (1975-1980) contains administrative materials collected by Dave Cooper in his role as business representative for District 91. Materials include correspondence, employee benefit information, grievance materials, arbitration information, and some conference material. Files are arranged alphabetically by name, title, or type.
Series II: Agreements and Negotiations (circa 1950-1983) contains negotiations transcripts and working papers for contracts for District 91 local lodges and final official printed contracts. The material is arranged by type and then by lodge.
Series III: Financial Records (circa 1955-1973) includes summary correspondence, financial reports, and the Treasurer's books and ledgers. The material, while not complete, represents the kinds of financial papers maintained at the District office. Material is arranged by type.
Series IV: Arbitrations (circa 1968-1977) RESTRICTED includes transcripts and support documents collected by district representatives serving local lodges. Arbitrations are arranged by local lodge number and then alphabetically. This series contains only a small sample of arbitration materials.
Series V: Grievances (circa 1965-1980) RESTRICTED contains grievance forms, support documentation, and notes from grievance step meetings. Most material is dated from 1975 to 1980. A District 91 representative serving the locals probably collected these materials. Materials are arranged by year then by step.
Series VI: Civil Case 9084- 9085: United State Superior Court, District of Connecticut (circa 1944-1969) contains records of the damages suit filed by the union after the 1960 strike. These materials were deposited by the legal counsel at the District office, and contain a fairly complete record of this court case. Materials in this series are arranged by type, in nine subseries: Pleading and Indexes (1962-1967, arranged chronologically); Briefs and Memoranda (undated, 1962-1969, arranged chronologically); Hearings (1962-1966); Interrogatories (1962-1963); Depositions (1962-1968, arranged alphabetically by name); Transcripts (1967, arranged chronologically); Exhibits (undated, organized in two sections, Plaintiff's exhibits and Defendant's exhibits, which are both arranged by number); Attorney's Working Papers (1944-1968, arranged in small units, as used by the lawyer); and Back Pay Data (1967, arranged alphabetically by person).
Used in conjunction with NLRB case 1-CA-3355 and Hartford Superior Court Case 133884-133885 papers, this material documents the unfair labor practice and damages suits filed after the 1960 strike.
Series VII: Case No. 1- CA- 3355, National Labor Relations Board (undated, 1949-1969) contains materials documenting the consolidated unfair labor practice suits filed by the union against United Aircraft Corporation after the 1960 strike. The legal counsel with District 91 deposited these materials after the final NLRB court decisions.
The material is arranged by type in four subseries: Pleading and Indexes (undated, 1963, arranged by type); Briefs and Memoranda (undated, 1963-1969, arranged chronologically); Official Report Proceedings (1964-1967, arranged chronologically and by page number); Exhibits (undated, organized in five sections: charging Party, General Counsel, Respondents, Trial Examiner, and Oversize Exhibits—each section is arranged by number); and Attorney's Working Papers (undated, 1949-1969, arranged in small units as used by lawyers).
Used in conjunction with District Court Case 9084- 9085 and Hartford Superior Court Case 133884- 133885 papers, these materials document the long history of the 1950 strike- related suits.
Series VIII: Case no. 133884-133885, Hartford Superior Court (circa 1963-1969) contains records of the suit United Aircraft Corporation filed against the IAMAW Grand Lodge to declare the 1960 strike illegal and to secure financial "damages" as a result of violence by union members during the 1960 strike. The suits were consolidated; Case No. 133884 was filed on Behalf of Pratt and Whitney, and Case No. 133885 was filed of behalf of Hamilton Standard. These materials were deposited by the union's legal counsel at the district office and contain a reasonably complete record of the court case. Materials in this series are arranged by type in seven subseries: Pleadings (1963-1969, arranged chronologically); Briefs and Memoranda (1963-1969, arranged chronologically); Depositions and Witness Testimony (undated, 1963-1968, arranged alphabetically by name); Transcripts (1964-1968, arranged chronologically); Exhibits (undated, 1963-1968), organized in two sections, Defendant's exhibits arranged numerically, and Plaintiff's exhibits, arranged alphabetically); Interrogatory Support Data (undated, arranged by interrogatory numbers); and Attorney's Working Papers (1960-1968, arranged alphabetically by subject).
Used in conjunction with NLRB case 1- CA- 3355 and District Court case 9084- 9085, these papers document the unfair labor practices and damage suits filed as a result of the 1960 strike.
Series IX: Other Legal Cases (circa 1960-1969) contains legal papers and attorney's working papers of cases involving District 91 and its local lodges. Materials in this series are organized in seven subseries: United States Supreme Court (1964, arranged by case number), United States District Court, District of Connecticut (1960-1967, arranged by civil number); United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit (1963-1964, arranged by case number); United States Court of Appeals, District of Columbia (1966-1968, arranged by case number); Hartford Superior Court (1960, arranged by case number); National Labor Relations Board (1960-1969, arranged by case number); and Attorney's Working Papers (undated, 1961-1964, arranged in small units as used by the layer). The most significant case in this material is U.S. District Court for Connecticut Civil Case No. 11, 466 Hoban (of the NLRB) vs. United Aircraft Corporation, C. 1965- 1966. In this case, UAC, questioned the union's role as representative bargaining unit during 1965 contract negotiations because 1960 strike litigations were not yet settled.
Series X: Conference Materials (circa 1960-1979) contains correspondence, notes, proceeding, publications, and printed material collected by District 91 officers and members at conferences and training seminars they attended. The series is organized in three subseries. General Files (undated, 1962-1979) contains miscellaneous information not identified with specific conferences, and is arranged chronologically. IAMAW Aerospace Conference (1966-1977) includes information from the 13th - 18th and 25th Conferences. Connecticut State Council of Machinists (1970-1972) subseries contains material from the council's training seminar and the semi-annual conference, both arranged chronologically. The final subseries, Other Conferences (1967-1971), contains materials collected at various Connecticut, New England and national conferences, arranged alphabetically by the organization's name.
Series XI: Printed Material (1937-1983) is organized in three sub-series: Newsclippings (1965-1982), Flyers (undated, 1953-1982), and Publications (1937-1982). Newsclippings contains scrapbook and loose newsclippings, which document labor and political activities, or other items of interest to labor. The 1960 scrapbooks are valuable for documenting the 1960 machinists strike. The newsclippings are arranged chronologically. Flyers contain copies of most flyers produced by Distrcit91 for all local lodges, arranged chronologically. This subseries also contains flyers produced by individual local lodges, arranged by plant. Publications contains contracts, some convention material, IAM printed material, IAMAW Grand Lodge publications and newsletters (including "The Machinist"), and District 91 Newsletters. This material is arranged alphabetically by originating body and/or title.
Series XII: Photographs and Memorabilia (undated, 1960-1982) is organized in two subseries, Photographs (undated, 1960-1982) and Memorabilia (undated, 1968-1974). Photographs contains prints and negatives organized by general groupings including union leaders, individuals, group photos, strikes and meetings. Memorabilia contains buttons, badges, and artifacts, arranged by type.
Series XIII: Microfilm and Tape Recordings (undated, 1953-1967) is divided into the two media types and contains information pertaining to the lawsuits, union activities and events.
History
District Lodge 91 received its charter in May 1953. At that time the representative locals consisted of Hartford Aircraft Lodge 743, chartered in 1941, representing workers at Hamilton Standard (located in East Hartford until 1952 when it moved to Windsor Locks); Industrial Aircraft Lodge 1746, chartered in February 1945, representing workers at Pratt and Whitney, East Hartford; and Industrial Aircraft Lodge 1746A, chartered in October 1951, representing Pratt and Whitney workers in Southington. In March 1959, Canal Lodge 700, in Middletown, was chartered and added to District 91 representation. Prior to 1953, Pratt and Whitney workers' lodges were part of IAM District 26. As of 1984, District 91 included Lodge 700, Lodge 707 (from North Haven), Lodge 743, Lodge 1746, and Lodge 1746A.
For a more detailed chronology of District 91's history see Michael S. Fitzgerald's unpublished paper "District 91" (in collection files).
Scope and Content
The collection contains the working administrative and legal files of the union. Some financial documents are also included. The most significant event documented in this collection is the nine week strike from July to August 1960, involving Lodges 1746 and 743. The unfair labor practice and damage suits and counter suits filed after this strike continued throughout the 1960s.
Press releases; Grievance procedures; District courts; Courts of last resort; Aerospace industries; Southington (inhabited place); East Hartford (Conn.); Law; Hartford (inhabited place); Connecticut (state); Strikes and lockouts; Aircraft industry workers; Arbitration, Industrial; Unfair labor practices; Actions and defenses; Machinists; Middletown (inhabited place); Aircraft industry; Labor unions; Collective labor agreements; Courts; Administrative records; Audiocassettes; Labor; Audio visual materials; Publications (documents); North Haven (inhabited place); Correspondence; Financial Records; United States (nation); Photographs; Employees
- Series I: Administrative Records, undated, 1947-1982
  - Subseries A: Correspondence and Files, undated, 1947-1966
    - Audits and financial statements, 1959-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Audits reports, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bank statements, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Blue Cross, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Board of Mediation and Arbitration, 1947, 1953, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Broad Brook plant, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Brunner, Gilbert (General Vice-President D-91), 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Buckland plant, 1945-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Business agents salary breakdown, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Business agents election, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - Business agents: statement of pension fund deduction, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bylaws of District 91, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Cole, Gordon (Editor of The Machinist), 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Coonley, Fred (General Vice- President D- 91), 1950-1958 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - Correspondence, 1954-1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Canal Lodge 700, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Lodges, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Matthew DeMore (General Secretary Treasurer), 1959-1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Current Meeting" notes, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Elections for District 91, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Expense account, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Executive Board minutes for the District, 1958-1964 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
    - Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Fidelity and Deposit Company, Maryland, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Financial Reports: from Eric Peterson, General Secretary Treasurer, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Flight enterprise, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Flyers for District 91, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Foremen orientation course, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Grand Lodge: Report of the General Secretary Treasurer, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Geuser, Wallace (Union Steward), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Haynes, A.J. (International President), 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Harlow letters, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Huhndorf, Carl (Department of Research), 1952-1959 (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
    - IAMAW letters, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - IAM-UAW: Joint Unity Program, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Internal Revenue, 1958, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 41-42)
    - Kowalski, Frank (Connecticut Congressman), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Kowalski, Frank: Special files for Grand Lodge Representative Thurer, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Lay-offs, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Lodge 743: Negotiations and contracts, 1959-1964 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Lodge 1746, 1957-1962 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Lodge 1746A, 1959-1967 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Main, John: retirement, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Membership applications, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Minutes of District 91 meetings, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - National Labor Relations Board, 1956-1960 (Box 3, Folder 52-54)
    - Nelson, Robert (Business Representative D- 91), 1956-1965 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Nelson, George (Grand Lodge representative, liaison officer, Washington, D.C.), 1961 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "No-raid" agreements, 1954-1962 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Papps, Plato: Legal Counsel, 1953-1963 (Box 3, Folder 58-59)
    - Peterson, Eric (Secretary- Treasurer), 1950-1958 (Box 3, Folder 60-61)
    - Pratt and Whitney: recall incidents, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Retainer agreement for Ratner and Zeman, legal counsels, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Rental, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Seminole Lodge 971, West Palm Beach, Florida: correspondence and flyers, 1961-1965 (Box 4, Folder 65-66)
    - Senate, U.S., 1950-1960 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Shemansky, Joseph P., undated (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Special Report to Union Members, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Steward Posters for all lodges, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Strike, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Strike donations, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Suit in Connecticut State courts re. Violation of strike agreement, 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Thurer, Richard (Grand Lodge Representative), 1951-1965 (Box 4, Folder 74-75)
    - Treasury Report, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - United Aircraft: salaried organizers, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - United Aircraft: correspondence, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - United Auto Workers, North Haven, CT, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Unemployment, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 80-81)
    - Unemployment compensation, 1953-1956 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Unfair labor practice charges by lodge 1746, 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - U.S. District Court: drafts and proceedings, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Walker, Elmer (General Vice- President), 1953-1956 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Watkins, George (General Vice- President), 1959-1962 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Welfare Benefits program, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 87-88)
    - Zeman, Daly and McNamara: Legal Counsel, 1962-1966 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Subseries B: Correspondence and Subject Files, undated, 1967-1982
    - American Arbitration Association, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Audit report: Grand Lodge, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Business Representatives references, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Bylaws, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 93-96)
    - Center of Dispute Settlement of Hartford, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Cole, Gordon (editor of The Machinist), 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Connecticut Conference of Mayors, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Connecticut Economic Conversion Committee, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Connecticut State Labor Council, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 101-102)
    - Connecticut State Council of Machinists, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Connecticut State Teachers: correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Correspondence: District 91, 1967-1971 (Box 5, Folder 105-106)
    - Correspondence: U.S. Congress, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Correspondence: Other IAM lodges, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - Cost of living increase, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Curran, Joseph: testimonial, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Day Care Planning and Coordinating Project, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - Delegates: local lodge officers, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - Delegates meeting, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - Economic development of the black community, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - Executive Board meetings, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Executive council, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Grand lodge: correspondence, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - Greater Hartford Council of Economic Education, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 118)
    - Greater Hartford Labor Council, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Grievances, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - Hamilton Standard: weekly changes, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - IAM: Grand Lodge officers
      - Brumm, John (Director of Education), 1970-972 (Box 5, Folder 122)
      - DeMore, Matthew (Grand Vice- President), 1968-1972 (Box 5, Folder 123-124)
      - Glover, Eugene (General Secretary Treasurer), 1972, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 125-126)
      - Iaccio, Sal (Grand Vice- President), 1973, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 127)
      - Matthews, Ross (Grand Vice- President), 1968-1972 (Box 5, Folder 128-130)
      - Sawyer, Gordon (Directing Business Representative), 1977-1979 (Box 5, Folder 131)
      - Smith, Floyd (International President), 1969-1973 (Box 6, Folder 132-135)
      - Winipisinger, William (International president), 1977-1982 (Box 6, Folder 136)
    - IAM subject file
      - Constitution: Article L, procedure for filing charges, conducting trials and submission of appeals, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 137)
      - Documentation guide, undated (Box 6, Folder 138)
      - Research department, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 139)
    - Income Tax, CT Citizens for, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 140)
    - Industrial Relations Research Association, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 141)
    - International Union of Electrical Radio and Machine Workers, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 142)
    - Jet News, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 143)
      - Kiefer, Lou, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 144)
      - Lodge 700: correspondence, 1966-1972 (Box 6, Folder 145-146)
      - Lodge 743: correspondence, 1966-1973 (Box 6, Folder 147-149)
      - Lodge 743: Internal financial review, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 150)
      - Lodge 743: Butler Seedman memorial, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 151)
      - Lodge 971: Correspondence, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 152)
      - Lodge 1746: Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 6, Folder 153-154)
      - Lodge 1746: Clouthiers Job, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 155)
      - Lodge 1746: officers, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 156)
      - Lodge 1746: resolution, undated (Box 6, Folder 157)
      - Lodge 1746 A: correspondence, 1968-1972 (Box 6, Folder 158)
      - Lodge 1746 A: Vincent Motto, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 159)
      - Los Angeles Federation of Labor, AFL-CIO, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 160)